A Finding Aid to the Gabrielle de Veaux Clements Papers, 1860-1948, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Gabrielle de Veaux Clements papers
1860-1948
Archives of American Art
Clements, Gabrielle de Veaux, 1858-1948
AAA.clemgabr
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of painter, etcher, printer, muralist, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements measure 1 linear foot and date from 1860 to 1948. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Clements to her mother; writings, including notes and essays on art history and etching techniques; printed material; artwork; eight sketchbooks; and photographs of Clements, her family and friends, and her work.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Gabrielle de Veaux Clements papers were donated by Mrs. Harlan Starr, Jr. in 1983.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 4212-4213 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Painter, printer, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements (1858-1948) lived and worked in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Baltimore, Maryland; and Folly Cove near Gloucester, Massachusetts. She was known for her etchings and her commissioned murals for the cities of Baltimore and Washington, D.C.
Clements was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to physician Richard Clements and his wife, Gabrielle De Vaux. Her interest in art was supported by her family and, at the age of seventeen, she began studying lithography with the designer Charles Page at the Philadelphia School of Design for Women. After graduating in 1880 from Cornell University, where she had produced a number of scientific drawings and lithographs, Clements studied with painter Thomas Eakins at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and won the school's Toppan Prize. In 1883, Clements was introduced to etching techniques by the artist Stephen Parrish and began exhibiting and printing her works professionally.
In 1884, Clements traveled abroad to Paris to study at the Academie Julian where she was joined in 1885 by fellow painter and future lifelong companion Ellen Day Hale. Upon returning to her Philadelphia studio in 1885, Clements taught other female artists, including Margaret Bush-Brown, and exhibited in numerous institutions, including the National Academy of Design and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. In 1895, Clements moved to Baltimore to teach art at the newly established Bryn Mawr School, where she remained until 1908. During her tenure in Baltimore, she was commissioned by the Bendann Galleries to etch nine views of Baltimore and also painted five church murals in Washington, D.C., which led to subsequent murals in Detroit, Philadelphia, and Chicago.
Clements and Hale frequently traveled abroad, visiting France, Italy, Egypt, Syria, and Palestine, and spent summers at "The Thickets," the house they purchased in the artists' colony at Folly Cove. During World War I, they wintered in Charleston, South Carolina where they opened their studios to young female artists and taught innovative etching, painting, and color printmaking techniques. After the war, they again opened their studios in Folly Cove to young artists and continued to teach and experiment with soft-ground etching and aquatints in color. This work was highlighted in special exhibitions at the J.B. Speed Art Museum and the Smithsonian Institution. Clements died in Rockport, Massachusetts in 1948.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, etcher, printer, muralist, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements measure 1 linear foot and date from 1860 to 1948. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Clements to her mother; writings, including notes and essays on art history and etching techniques; printed material; artwork; 8 sketchbooks; and photographs of Clements, her family and friends, and her work.
Biographical material consists of an address book, artwork sales and price lists, and autobiographical notes.
Correspondence is primarily with Clements' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from Clements to her mother during her college years at Cornell University.
Writings include notes and essays on art history and etching techniques, 2 notebooks of poetry, and a travel diary chronicling a trip to Egypt with Ellen Day Hale.
Printed material includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, a map of the artists' colony at Rockport, Folly Cove in Massachusetts, and a copy of the book Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison.
Artwork consists of sketches and original etchings by Clements and artwork by others.
There are 8 sketchbooks consisting primarily of cityscapes, landscapes, and figure and portrait studies.
Photographs are of Clements, her family and friends, artists models, and work by Clements and others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical materials, circa 1920-1944 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1875-1945 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1885-1940 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed material, circa 1860-1948 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1895-1940 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Sketchbooks, circa 1884-1940 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1875-1940 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Muralists -- Massachusetts; Printmakers -- Massachusetts; Etchers -- Massachusetts; Art teachers -- Massachusetts; Women artists; Women painters; Women printmakers; Women educators; Etching -- Technique; Art -- History; Prints; Photographs; Diaries; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Egypt -- description and travel; Hale, Ellen Day, 1855-1940; Cornell University -- Students
- Biographical Materials, circa 1920-1944; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material consists of an address book, artwork sales and price lists, and autobiographical notes.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Address Book, circa 1930-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork Sales and Price Lists, 1929-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiographical Notes, circa 1920-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, circa 1875-1945; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Clements' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from Clements to her mother during her college years at Cornell University, as well as correspondence from the printer and publisher Charles W. Ames. There is also a carbon copy of a 1945 letter from the sculptor Walker Hancock to his father describing the retrieval of art works confiscated by the Nazis.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A-Z Miscellaneous, circa 1885-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ames, Charles W., 1879-1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clements, Gabrielle de Veaux, circa 1875-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - de Vaux, Gabrielle (mother), circa 1877-1880; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, 1912-1927, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Head, Louisa, circa 1875-1885; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hicks, Margaret, circa 1875-1885; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - K., Florence, 1881-1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Library of Congress, 1929-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mills, Hattie May, 1877-1878; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Peggy, 1879-1882; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Polly ("Rubbie"), 1879-1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1895-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1885-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings, circa 1885-1940; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders Box 1
  Writings include notes and essays on art history and etching techniques, 2 notebooks of poetry by Clements and Ellen Day Hale, and a 1930 travel diary chronicling a trip to Egypt with Ellen Day Hale.
  Materials are arranged by document type and subject matter.
  - Diary, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notebook of Poetry, circa 1886-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - On Art History, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - On Artworks, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - On Etching Techniques, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Poem, "Christmas", circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1885-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Printed Material, 1860-1948; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1
  Printed material consists of clippings; exhibition catalogs; a map of the artists' colony at Rockport, Folly Cove in Massachusetts; a copy of the book Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison; and a postcard of St. Philip's Church.
  - Book, Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison, 1860; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1893-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1923, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Map, Rockport, Massachusetts Artist Colony, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Postcard, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Artwork, circa 1895-1940; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Artwork consists of sketches and original etchings by Clements, a copy of Durer's "St. Jerome in His Study," and a print, possibly by Lilian Westcott Hale.
  - Sketches and Original Etchings, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - By Others, Etching, "St. Jerome in His Study", 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - By Others, Sketch (possibly by Lilian Wescott Hale), circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Sketchbooks, 1884-1940; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  There are 8 sketchbooks consisting of cityscapes, landscapes, figure and portrait studies, animal and nature studies, and mural designs.
  Materials are arranged by subject matter.
  - Sketchbook #1, Cityscapes, Portrait Studies, and Ships, 1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sketchbook #2, Cityscape, Figure and Decorative Studies, 1885-1912; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Sketchbook #3, Landscapes, Cityscapes, and Figure Studies, 1926-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sketchbook #4, Landscapes, Cityscapes, and Figure Studies, circa 1930-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sketchbook #5, Landscape and Portrait Studies, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sketchbook #6, Mural Designs, circa 1895-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Sketchbook #7, Nature and Figure Studies, circa 1913-1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sketchbook #8, Nature, Figure, and Animal Studies, 1919-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Photographs, circa 1875-1940; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographs are of Clements and her family and friends, including travel snapshots from the Black Oaks neighborhood in Charleston, South Carolina, and travel photographs from Egypt, France, and Italy. The series also includes snapshots of artist models and scenes, photographs of artwork by Clements, and photographs of 45 paintings and sketches by Lilian Wescott Hale.
  - Photographs of Clements, Family, and Friends, circa 1875-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Photographs of Homes and Buildings, circa 1875-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Travel, Charleston, South Carolina, 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48-51)
  - Travel, Egypt, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Travel, France, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Travel, Italy, circa 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Clements, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Females, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Girls, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Males, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Still Lifes, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Reference Photographs of Animals, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Reference Photographs of Buildings, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Reference Photographs of Cityscapes, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Reference Photographs of Fences and Brickwork, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Reference Photographs of Figure Models, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Reference Photographs of Seascapes, circa 1920-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)